<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The last wil and last confession of martyn luthers faith co[n]cerming [sic] the [principal articles of religion which are in controuersy, which he wil defend &amp; mai[n]teine vntil his death, agaynst the pope and the gates of hell drawe[n] furth by him at the request of the princes of germany which haue reformed theier [sic] churches after the gospel, to be offred vp at the next general councel in all their names &amp; now published before that all the world may haue an euydent testimony of his faith if it shal fortune him to dye before there be any such cou[n]cel, tra[n]slated out of latyn beware of the pope &amp; of his false prophetes and bissopes for thei wil come in shepys clothing and in angels facys but yet inwardly thei are ravening wolnys [sic].</title>
            <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1543</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 90 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16984</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104350</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840088</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840088</idno>
            <idno type="VID">4559</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06511)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 4559)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 136:14)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The last wil and last confession of martyn luthers faith co[n]cerming [sic] the [principal articles of religion which are in controuersy, which he wil defend &amp; mai[n]teine vntil his death, agaynst the pope and the gates of hell drawe[n] furth by him at the request of the princes of germany which haue reformed theier [sic] churches after the gospel, to be offred vp at the next general councel in all their names &amp; now published before that all the world may haue an euydent testimony of his faith if it shal fortune him to dye before there be any such cou[n]cel, tra[n]slated out of latyn beware of the pope &amp; of his false prophetes and bissopes for thei wil come in shepys clothing and in angels facys but yet inwardly thei are ravening wolnys [sic].</title>
                  <author>Luther, Martin, 1483-1546.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>D. van der Straten?,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Wesel :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1543]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC; publication date from foot of leaf D8v.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: a-d.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:4559:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:4559:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The laſt wil And laſt confeſſion of martyn luthers faith
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerming the principal articles of religion which are in controuerſy / 
which he wil defend &amp; mai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teine vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>til his death / agaynſt the pope and
the gates of hell drawe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> furth by him at the requeſt of the princes of
germany which haue reformed thei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er churches after the goſpel / to be offred
vp at the next general coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cel in all their names &amp; now publiſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhed
before that all the world may haue an euydent teſtimony of his faith if it
ſhal fortune him to dye before there be any ſuch cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel / tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſlated
out of latyn</p>
            <p>Beware of the pope &amp; of his falſe prophetes and biſſopes
for thei wil come in ſhepys clothing and in an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels facys but yet inwardly
thei are ravening woluys.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:4559:2"/>
            <head>The articles conteined in this boke / be theſe
folowing.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Of the diuine mageſty of god / and of the iij. perſons in
one god heade.</item>
               <item>Of the offyce of Ieſus chriſt &amp; of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s
rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </item>
               <item>Of the maſſe wherin purgatory / appearing &amp; walking
of dead ſperites / pilgrimages / gyl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des &amp; almaner of brotherhode
ſaintes reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques &amp; pardons are confuted.</item>
               <item>Of the inuocacyon of ſaintes</item>
               <item>Of collegys &amp; monaſterys how thei ought to be
ordred.</item>
               <item>Of the auctoryte of the pope.</item>
               <item>Of ſinne.</item>
               <item>Of pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tricyon co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon &amp;
ſatiſfaccion.</item>
               <item>Of the goſpel</item>
               <item>Of baptime.</item>
               <item>Of the baptime of infantes.</item>
               <item>Of the ſacrament of the body &amp; blode of
chriſt.</item>
               <item>Of the keys of the church.</item>
               <item>Of confeſſyon or abſolucyon.</item>
               <item>Of excommunicacyon.</item>
               <item>Of geuing of orders &amp; of the calling of
miniſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</item>
               <item>Of the mariage of priſtes.</item>
               <item>Of the church.</item>
               <item>how ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is iuſtified before / god &amp; god workes</item>
               <item>Of the vowes of monkes &amp; frires.</item>
               <item>Of the traducions of men.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:4559:2"/>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Han Paul biſſhop of ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me the third of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me did
proclame &amp; appo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ynt a general councell to be holden at mantua in the yere.
1537. at the feſt of pe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tecoſt which within a while after he wold ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue had
at ſome other pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce and not at mantua / in ſo moch that it was vncetten
where he wold or might beſt appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te it / in the meane tyme we thought
ſurely ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be called vnto the councel to gether with other / or els to
be condemned there vncalled / wherfor this labor was required at that time of
me that ſhuld gather our whole doctrine in to certen ſpecyal chapters and
principal arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles / that if the councel ſchuld goo forward in erneſt / 
all men might haue a ſure knoulege wherin and how farre we wold or colud gyue
place to the papiſtes / and againe in what ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and mynd we haue
determyned fully with our ſelues to abyde and remaine conſtantly for euer.
And vp on this requeſt I dyd gather the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipal articles. ſet forth
i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this boke / which I delyuered to the whole nomber of them that haue receiued
our doctrine. And thei all with one co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent did receiue and approue them / in
ſo moch as it was determyned among them that <pb facs="tcp:4559:3"/>if the pope with his
part ſhuld ones dare be ſo bold as to hold a right free / and lauful
councel without any falſe fraude diſceite or diſſimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon / that than
theſe articles with the confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyon of our faith ſhuldbe offred vp vnto
them. But the court of rome abhorreth ſo ſore from a fre councel / and
auoydeth from the light ſo ſhamefully / that it hath made eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them which
ſtond on theer ſyde / vtterly to deſpaire of any general aſſemble / 
not only that this court of ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me wil neuer call any free cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel / but alſo
that it wil neuer be content to ſuffer gladly any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>u<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel / to be had / with
the which thing eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues are offended &amp; diſcontent / as
thei ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue a good cauſe / and are ſore greued therwith / for as moch as
thei perceyue that the pope had rather all chriſten men to periſſh and go
to the deuel / and that al theer ſowles ſſchuld perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually be danned / 
than to ſuffer him ſelfe / his carnals / biſſhopys and ſhauelings to
be refor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>med broght in to a right way or to oues ceaſe his tyranny. But I not
with ſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding thought it beſt to publyſſh &amp; ſet fort theſe
principal arti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles of our doctrine for this cauſe / that if it ſhu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> fortune death to peruent me before any
co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ſel ſhuld be gathered as I
both hope and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> / for as moch as
theſe wretches / abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> the
perfit lyght like owels / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tendand
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo beſyly both night and
day to hynder a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <pb facs="tcp:4559:3"/>prolo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g al mauer of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſellesyit the peple
my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glit haue deuer more in time to come my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſyon and the teſtymony
of my faith at hand to vſe reade and loke vpon wherin as I haue continewed
vntyl this day ſo wil I ſtil remayne ſo long as I lyue by the grace of
god. for what ſhuld I ſay / or how ſhuld I complaime? I am yet alyue / I
wryte I teach / I reade &amp; preach dayly / and yet the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re be certen venemos
ſerpentes not only amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g our aduerſarys but alſo among our falſe
coun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terfet brethern which wil ſeme to hold withus which do vtter &amp;
betray them ſelues ſtudying malicioſly &amp; falſely to wreſt myne
own writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g myne own doctrine / againſt my ſelf / euen befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re my face / I
my ſelf loking vp on them &amp; alſo hearing them / and yet the
themſelues knowe welinough that I teache the contrary. Thus li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke falſe
theues thei abuſe the labors &amp; ſwet of my browes to the maintenans of
eher venom &amp; poiſon. What wil they doo (thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ke yow) wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I am dead? It is
my part and duty therforto reſiſt / withſtand &amp; confound them whils I
ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue. But how can I alone ſtoppe all the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes of the deuel? of them
ſpecyally which (as they are all poiſoned and infect) wil neither he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>are
nor conſidre or marke ſuch things as we write / but applye theer mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des an
ſtudy to this thing only. moſt ſhamefully to wreſt / corrupt 
<pb facs="tcp:4559:4"/>miſtake / and peruert our wordes in euery ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne The deuel of hell
/ or at the leaſt the wrath of god confute ſuch wretches as thei are
wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy. I do often tymes remember the ſaing of good gerſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / which douteth
whether any good boke ought to be publiſſhed in writing or no? If nothing
ſhuld be writne tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> are the ſoules of many one neglect and not regarded
which by ſuch writings might haue moch help and remedy. And agayne on
contrary part whan any thing is written / than the deuel with an infinyte
nomber of moſt ſpiteful &amp; peſtile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t tun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges is redy at ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d / to
i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fect / poiſon a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d peruert all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can receiue &amp; take any
pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fi therof. And yet not witſtonding all the world ſeyth what thei wynne:
for after thei be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gan ones to forge lyes vp on us / and we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ut to
withdrawe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s hartes from us and to wi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne them to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues with lyi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / 
god hath done and wrought his worke and wil effectu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>oſly. and hath brought to
paſſe that many do daily ſwarue fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> andi oncline to us a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thus by
their lyes thei haue procured the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual ſhame and
diſhonor / which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g god do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th yet daily alſo. I muſt nedes ſhewe
&amp; vtter a certi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtory that cometh now to my mid There was at wittenberg
a certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tor ſent hether fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
fra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which ſaid ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly before our faces th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the king his maſter did ſurely bileue that there was no maner
of church or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacion with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <pb facs="tcp:4559:4"/>us / no maner of rulars nor officers. And that there ſhuld be no
maner of matrimony but that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhuld ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne at large now to one wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
now to a nother eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aftir the maner of bru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te beaſtes / and agaime that it
ſhuld be lauful for euery priuate ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to vſe or miſuſe / do or vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>do
all maner of thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ghs after his own wil &amp; iuſt &amp;c. Now tel me I pray
yow with what face ſhal theſe men dare loke vp on us at the latter day
before the iudgement ſeate of chriſt which haue tolder perſuaded bi their
letters &amp; wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs / this Fig &amp; other peple &amp; noble me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch
mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtros &amp; abhominable lyes / for tru tales? Chriſt all our lorde / 
&amp; the moſt rightful iudge, is our witneſſe that thei lye ſhamefully
vp on us and haue euer done: whoſe ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce and iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>demni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g them
to euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacion thei ſhal not choſe but heare &amp; abide. This
am I ſure of Now god turn &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uert the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by any
poſſible meanes be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uerted / as for o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther euerlaſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and moſt cruel
poniſchment &amp; da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth remaine for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. But now to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to my
putpoſe agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / I wold wiſſh ſurely o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to ſee a true cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel
wherby many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſys might be take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a way a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d many me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue
profi: not that we our ſelues haue nede o any ſuch cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel or plame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for
our churches are ſo lighned &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firmed i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the pure word / of god i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rhe
true vſe of ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d in the knoulege of all good order &amp; all
good workes that for our <pb facs="tcp:4559:5"/>cauſe we deſire no maner of perlament
or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uncel / for we cannot think that any councel can teach vs a more perfight
order than we ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue. But we ſee with depe ſorow &amp; lamentaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our
hartes mani pariſſhes miſerably de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute / forſake<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;
vnregarded both of biſſhops and of prebendarys: we ſee in theer
diocyſes &amp; pariſſhes after what ſort the ſely miſerable pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple
do lyue and dye for whoſe ſaluacion Chriſt him ſelf ſuffred death vp
on the croſſe: and yet thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be ſuffred to heare nether him their
tru ſhepard &amp; paſtor / nor yet none of his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aking and preaching
vnto them for the which cauſe tremble &amp; feare vehemently leſſe god
wil ſhortly call &amp; bring all the world to a councel by ſome angel / 
which ſhal vtterley deſtroy us all / as he did ones Sodom &amp; Gomor / for
as moch as we contemne &amp; mocke him ſo lightly thorow our councels. And
beſide thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which are neceſſary to be reformed in the
ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tualty / (as thei cal it) there be an infinite nom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ber of abuſes in
the temporal regiment to be re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dreſſed. for there is vncharitable grudgd
and diſſenſyon betwene princes and other nobles: and vſury &amp;
couetoſnes haue ſo farre preua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yled &amp; hath ſo drowned the temporalty
euen ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke a flode or a ſee) that now in the place of the lawe are crept in / 
ryot / vnmeſurable exceſſe / wantones / pryde in apparel / glotony
banker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting / <pb facs="tcp:4559:5"/> diſe / cardes and pompe / withal kindes of vices
&amp; miſchefe / diſobedience of ſubiectes and houſoldes toward theer
heades / peſtilent enhanſing of all maner of marchandiſe in bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng &amp;
ſeiling / theſe I ſay / with an infinyte ſort ſuch life / haue ſo
preuailed that thei can not be reformed in X. councels nor in XX.
aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembles. Theſe principal matters both of the temporalty &amp; of the
ſpiritualty / if thei ſhuld be entreated of in a general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel / thei
ſhuld ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke us to haue ſo moch labor and beſines / that we ſhuld ſone
forget &amp; litle regard the foliſſh triflyng about long gownes &amp;
brode ſhauyn crownes / fryres girdels / biſſhops forked cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pes / carnal
hattes / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d croſer ſtaues with ſuch other trifyls. for it were time
inough to entre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate of the choiſe of meates / the differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of gar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meetes
ſhort or lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the ſhaui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of crounes &amp; of cloiſters / after that
the pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipal articles of the faith with a godly politike ordre for the
co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>monwelth were determined &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluded by the word of god. But if we wil
ſwalow op Vho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>le camels / and ſtrayne gnaties / if we wil recei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue &amp;
ſuffer gret beames in our eys &amp; pluck out the ſmal motys / if we wil
ſtomble at a ſtrane &amp; leape at a block / we nede not be ſo gretly
ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riful for any councels. wherfor I haue made but a very fewe chapters &amp;
principal articles for els we haue ſo many co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs <pb facs="tcp:4559:6"/>of god to be obſerued in his church / in the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mynalty / and in
euery particular houſe &amp; pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſh / that we are neuer able to perform
them. wherfor what nede is it to make many actes decreys and tradicions
beſide? ſpecially if the principal articles and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandments enioined us bi
god himſelfe be neglect and nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded / as though god muſt geue
place to our foliſſh trifles becauſe we treade his ſpecial
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandmenas / vnder our fete like ſwyne. But our ſinnes do ſo ſore
vexe oppreſſe &amp; lade us that thei wil not ſuffer god to haue mercy
vp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on ue / becauſe we do not repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t nor amend / but rather ſtudy and labor
to ſtabliſſh &amp; maintey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne all maner of wickednes. O merciful lord
Ie<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſu chriſt / were ſaue then thy ſelf to celebrate a councel &amp; to
redeme thi elect thorow thy own glorios preſens for of the pope and of his
ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herents ther is no hope at all. thei wil in no wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe receiue the. wherfor
help thou us pore miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable creatures / crieng &amp; calling vnto the / 
ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the erneſtly / for the abowndant mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cys ſafe that thou haſt
geuen tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row thi holy ſpirite which li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth &amp; reigneth with the &amp;
with the fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to be prai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed &amp; glorified for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:4559:6"/>
            <head>The firſt part conteineth the ſpecial articles of the
diuine maieſty of god.</head>
            <div type="article">
               <p>I. We confeſſe firſt that the father / ſon / &amp; the
holy goſt in one diuyne ſubſtance &amp; nature be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> diſtinct perſons &amp; yet one god which created
heauen and erth.</p>
               <p>II. That the father was without begimming ano the ſon had his
begimming of the father / and that the holy goſt did procede of them both</p>
               <p>III. That the father nor the holy goſt did neuer ta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke op on
them mannys nature / but theſon only.</p>
               <p>IIII. That the ſon was ſo incarnate that he was conceiued by
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the holy goſt without any
ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s helpe / &amp; born of the pure &amp; holy virgyng Ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry. and after ward
that te ſuffred his paſſion / dyed &amp; was buryed / deſtended to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e hellys. Roſe fro death / 
aſceded heauen ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at the right hand of the father / and that he
ſhal come to iudge the quict &amp; the dead &amp;c. as the comon crede of the
apoſtles / the crede ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ng in the maſſe / and the crede of athanaſius
do teach.</p>
               <p>Of theſe articles there is no controuerſy contencyon for
both <pb facs="tcp:4559:7"/>partes do confeſſe all theſe things / wherfor it were
but foly to entreate more largely of them</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The ſecond part conteineth the articles of the office &amp;
worke of Ieſu Chriſt and of our rede<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pcyon / and of all his bemifights
&amp; actes which he hath done for us</head>
               <p>In this article this is the firſt &amp; principal ſome that
Ieſus Chriſt our god &amp; lord ſuffred death fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> our ſinnys &amp; roſe againe to ſaue us / Roma. 4.
Item that he is the o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſpecial lamb of god / which taketh a way the
ſinnes of the world. Ioha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the i. And that god hath layd the iniquyte of al
man kind vpon his back / Eſai. 53. furthermore all peple haue ſynned and
thei are made rightuos agayn / or ſaued / frely by the mere grace &amp; mercy
of god thorow the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dempcyon of Ieſus Chriſt &amp; thorow his blo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de Roma.
3. And for as moch as this grace &amp; mercy muſt be receiued by faith (for
no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can obteine it by any worck not yet by the lawe nor by any merite)
therfor it is certen &amp; manifeſt that we be iuſtifyed by faith as holy
paul teſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fieth rhe 3. to the roma. ſayng we ſuppoſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be
iuſtifyed by fayth without the workes of the lawe. Item that he migh be
iuſt &amp; the iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtifyer of him which bileueth in Ieſus. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>From this article can we not moue one hear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>breade / thogh ſe
hauen &amp; erth ſhuld falle and all the world goo to gether to wrack / for
there <pb facs="tcp:4559:7"/>is no nother name vnder heanen where by we can be ſaued / 
Actu. 4. Item / Eſay. 59. we are healed thorow his ſtripes.</p>
               <p>This article is the whole foundacion &amp; gro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>und both of all
that we teach and alſo lyue aga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inſt the pope / the deuel and the world.
wherfor we ought in no wiſe to dowte of this article.</p>
               <p>Els all together were done / and at a point / and the pope / the
deuel with his whole rable ſhuld haue the victory of us and tryumph co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
us.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <div type="article">
               <head>The ſecond article.</head>
               <p>The maſſe that is comonly vſed in the papi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry is the
higheſt &amp; moſt horrible abhomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion that euer was / and it is as
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the principal article of the faith as heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is to hell although
among all the popiſch Idolaters it is the moſt precios / dai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> and bringeth moſt lucre to the
purſe. for all men haue bileued ſure<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly that the ſacrifice &amp; work of
the maſſe though it were done of the moſt raſcal ſcull you in the
world / yet it ſhuld deliuer me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from all their ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes both i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this life
and alſo after this life i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gatory / which thing can no thing doo not
per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forme ſaue the only lamb of god as is before ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>id. Whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>for we wil geue no place in this
arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle / nor gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t any part therof. And if any man chance vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſome
reaſonable papiſt / let him axe him gentylly / for what cauſe thei labor
to main<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teine <pb facs="tcp:4559:8"/>the maſſe ſo obſtinatly / ſpecially ſeing
it<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is nothing els than a mans
inuencyon and no ordinance of god. And it is lauful to neglect and breake mans
tradicyons / as chriſt ſaith- Math. 15. thei honor &amp; ſerue me in
vayne teach<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing the doctrines / tradicions &amp; commandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of men. And
again it is a thing of no ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſite and it may be left welmough with out
any ſinne or perel.</p>
               <p>Thirdly. The ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t may be receiued after a better mor
profita<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble and a more holſom way / acording to the in<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtitucion of
chriſt: which way is only profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; none but it. whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fore why ſhuld we bring the world in
to ſo heuy a miſery &amp; danger for a fanſy of mans braine / and a
trifel of naught Let the peple be taught in comon ſermo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / that the
maſſe being an imaginacyon of mans bra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yne may be taken a way &amp;
diſamulled with out any ſinne / and that it is a matter of no da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon to
deſpiſe the maſſe / for a man may obtei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne euerlaſting ſaluacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
with out the maſſe / and after a better way than bi it. Now if the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
were thus taght / there were no dowte but that it ſhuld come in to contempt
alone of it ſelf without any labor / not only amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple peple / but
alſo among all good / wiſe &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tuos men.</p>
               <p>And this thing might be brought to paſſe <pb facs="tcp:4559:8"/>the
better / if thei were inſtruct / that the maſſe is a perlos &amp; a
dangeros thing / imagyned of mans brayn with out any commandment or wil of
god.</p>
               <p>Forthly for as moch as there haue bene an infinyte nomber of
moſt deteſtable abuſis tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>row out the whole world by the reaſon of
by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſelling of maſſes / it is a lauful &amp; a ſufficient
cauſe wherfore all maſſes ought to be diſanulled &amp; forbidden / 
though it were for no nother cauſe than this only that thoſe abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
might ſo be remoued / although there were ſome goodnes or vtilyte in them
as there is no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne at all. And thei ought rather to be aboliſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hed that
theſe abuſes might be forbidden / ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſeing ſuch maſſes be
vnprofitable / vnne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary / and ful of perel and danger / and agai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me all
things both more neceſſary more pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable &amp; alſo more certen / may
be obteined / though there were n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
ſuch maſſe.</p>
               <p>Fifly / the maſſe neither is nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be / nothyng els than a
worck of men (as the old canon and all old boke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> doo alſo teſtifye) yea and inuented by moſt wicked raſcals
/ for this purpoſe that euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cile both hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe and other
vnto god and both obteine &amp; merite remiſſi- of his ſinnes and the
fauor of god thorow he ari<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g or cauſing it to be ſayd. for wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
it is done / ſayd or hard euen moſt holyly / it is done ſaid <pb facs="tcp:4559:9"/>and hard for no other end than a fore reherſed. for vnto what other
vſe or vtilite can it ſerue? wherfor it muſt nedes be condemned and take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
a way / for it is againſt tpe principal article of our redempcion / which
ſaith that no maner of preſt or ſhaueling noither good nor bad / nor no
maner of worke or ſacrifice / can take away our ſinnes / ſaue only the
lamb of God / the ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God. further more if any priſt wil vſe this
excuſe / cloke &amp; prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe to ſay that he miniſtreth the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
to hym ſelf alone / for this purpo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe that he may the more perfightly with
better dilige<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce receiue it / let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> know that this is no
erneſt but a prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed excuſe for who ſo euer wil vſe this ſupper
perfightly and reue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rently to confirme his faith &amp; to haue any pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fight
therby / muſt receyue it in the true ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment miniſtred / acording to
the inſtitucyon of Chriſt. But for a priſt to miniſter the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
to him ſelf alone / it is but a face and an imaginacion of man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> braine / both vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten / dangeros / 
vnprofitable and alſo forbid<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And who ſo euer doth ſo / he doth he
ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not tel what / for he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth the word of god and foloweth a falſe
face / opinyon and ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of mans brayne. And (although all other things
in it were neuer ſo probable) yet it is vnlauful for any man to vſe the
como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>crament of the whole church / priuately to his <pb facs="tcp:4559:9"/>own
vſe alone / after his own foliſſh imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon &amp; falſe
perſuaſyon contrary to the word / of god / priuately and not to gether with
the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon whole congregacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: and ſo thei handle the ſacrament of chriſt
as a thynge of light reputa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon. for this ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t was not inſtitute to
be vſed of one alone but it was geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the whole multitude to be vſed
como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly of many to gether.</p>
               <p>I am ſure that this article of the maſſe / ſhal be one
of the ſpecial articles which ſhal be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into controuerſy / whan
ſo euer ther be any general cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel. for if it were poſſible / thei wold
rather grant us all other articles than this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne. And carnal campegius at the
councel hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den at Augſpurg / did openly ſay that he wold rather ſuffre
hym ſelf to be racked &amp; euery me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre of his body to be teared fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> other
than that the maſſe ſhuld periſſhe or be condemned. And I for my part
/ by the grace of god / wil ſuffre my ſelf to be conſumed into aſſhes
/ before I wil permit any popiſſh priſt or patched ſhaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to be
either equal or ſuperior to chriſt my Lord &amp; my Sauior. Wherfor we are
&amp; remay<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne for euer emnys &amp; contrary one to a nother. Thei perceiue
right wel / that if the maſſe were condemned / than the whole papiſtry
were cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ouer thrown: and therfor thei wold rather ſe us all poiſoned
&amp; burnt (if thei could) than to grant us this one article. Beſide all
this / <pb facs="tcp:4559:10"/>this Dragons &amp; deuels tayle the Maſſe, hath bene
the cauſe &amp; the very mother of moch blaſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phemy / and of purgatory.
where / thorow ſow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le maſſes for the deade / thorow dirges &amp;
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendacions / thorow month myndes / tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals / yeare dayes / &amp; bowel
maſſes &amp; chantry maſſes to be ſayd in their cowrſe (&amp;
ſpecially on ſowlemaſſe day / ) thei haue bene wholly al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together
occupyed in purgatory and with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with purgatory / inſo moch
that the maſſe hath bene vſed &amp; vſurped in a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner for the dead
only / where as chriſt did inſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tute his ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rament for the liuing alone.</p>
               <p>Wherfor Purgatory with all his pompe / high honor and
marchandiſe muſt be taken for a mocke &amp; a miſt of the deuel. For it
is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the principal article of our redempcy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which teacheth that al
ſowles be redemed &amp; delyuered thorow no workes of man / but on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly therow
chriſt alone. Furthermore we ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue no commandment of god concerning dead
ſowles / and therfor this purgatory / although it were no error or Idolatry / 
might laufully be condemned.</p>
               <p>The papiſtrs are wont to alledge .S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten. for this
article &amp; thei cyte the teſtimonys of dyuers doctors which haue written
(as thei ſay) of purgatory.</p>
               <p>Thei think that we vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not / for what <pb facs="tcp:4559:10"/>purpoſe thei ſpeake ſuch ſentencys. S. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten writeth not
that there is a purgatory / nei<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther hath he any place of ſcripture wherby he
can proue it: but he leaueth it in dowt whether there be a purgatory or no / 
and he ſaith that his mother required to haue a memory at the al<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tar or the
receiui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g whatſoeuer be / it is nothing els
than a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſticyos imaginacyon of a fewe men / which can make no article
of our faith / for that is the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of god alone. But the papiſtes do ſo
wreſt &amp; writhe ſuch teſtimonys of men / that the peple ſhuld byleue
more faithfully / their fil<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thy / wicked and abhominable macha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>diſe of
ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyng &amp; offring maſſes into purgatory for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ad ſowles &amp;c.
Which thei ſhal neuer proue by S. Auſten. Whan thei haue ones condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued
thoſe putgatory marchandiſe of maſſes (werof S. Auſten did neuer in
his life ones dreame) than wil we diſpute with them whe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther .S. Auſten
without any auctorite of ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture / ought to be receiued &amp; allowed or
no / and whether it be lauful to haue memorys of dead ſowles whan the
ſacrament is receiued or no for we may not take all the doings and ſaings
of holy fathers for articles of our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ith. For by that mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes / their maner
&amp; order of lyuyng / their clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thes or garme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes and their howſes alſo
wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in <pb facs="tcp:4559:11"/> thei did dwell ought to be eſtemed as arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of the
faith / like as the relykes of ſaintes haue heretofore bene eſtemed. But
the word of god only muſt make articles of the faith / and no creature
beſide / no though it were an angel of heauen.</p>
               <p>Secondarly / vp on the maſſe haue riſen many iugglinck
ſotiltes of falſe ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rytes
which haue appe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ryd vnder likenes of
mennes ſou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les / deſyryng to haue maſſes / dirgys / pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grymages and
ſuch kynd of almaſſys to be done for them / with ſuch lyes and
diſceiteſul moc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes as no man can reherſe / which al the world muſt be
compelled to eſteme as articles of the ſaith / and to lyue after their
appointment.</p>
               <p>And the pope hath confirmed alſo / all ſuch things / as he
hath done the maſſe and all other abhomynacyon.</p>
               <p>Thirdly. The maſſe was the cauſe of pilgrimages / for in
pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ges / the peple haue ſought maſſes / remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes
&amp; the mercy or fauor of god. And the maſſe hath bene the head captayn
of all theſe tgings. And it is wonder that ſuch things ſhuld be imagyned
/ ſeing it is ſo manifeſt that there is no maner of mencyon of
pilgrimages in the word of god / and again it is euident ino<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ugh that thei be
vnprofitable for as moch as we haue many better things than pilgrima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges / 
<pb facs="tcp:4559:11"/>&amp; finally thei may be left &amp; forſaken with out all
ſinne / perel or danger. Why do men runne from their own cytes &amp;
pariſſhes / forſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke the word of god / their wiues and childern (which
all be neceſſary things &amp; commanded us by god to ſtike vnto) and in
ſteade of them folow and delit their ſelues in vnprofitable / foliſſh / 
daugeros things &amp; deuliſſh errors / but that the deuel hath procured
&amp; ſturred vp the pope to command &amp; confirme ſuch things / whereby
many peple might be ſeduced from chriſt &amp; fixe their hope &amp; truſt
in their wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes? and alſo (which is worſt of all) to commit daily
Idolatry. furthermore / I ſay / it is no ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary thing / hauing no
commandment of god nor no word in the ſcripture which coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celleth men
thereunto / and it is alſo a doutful dangeros &amp; a noyſom thing. Werfor
in this article we ought to grant nothing nor to giue no place at all / vnto
our aduerſarys. Let the comon peple be taught that pilgrimages be not
neceſſary / but full of perel and da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger / and than after ward / let us
ſee where any pilgrimage ſhal remaine or where a man ſhal find any.</p>
               <p>Fortly / brotherhodes / felowſhips &amp; gyldes wherin abbeys
colleges &amp; whole dioces / par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons &amp; vicars haue bound them ſelues
one to a nother by letters patentes / and euery one made other bretherr
partakers of all their maſſes and <pb facs="tcp:4559:12"/>good workes &amp;c. as wel
for the dead as for the liuing / (which is a filthy &amp; an abhominable
marchandiſe) And it is not only an inuencyon of mans braine not conteined in
the expreſſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mandment of god / and vnneceſſary / but it is alſo
contrary to the firſt article of our redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon wherfor it is in no wiſe
to be permitted or ſuffred.</p>
               <p>Fiftly. The reliques of ſaintes (in the which point ſo many
manifeſt lyes &amp; foliſſh trifles ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue bene tryed of dogs &amp;
horſe bones / that eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for ſuch falſhode wherby the deuel hath blered
the world / thei ought to haue bene condemned long agoo / although ther had
bene ſome good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes in them) what be thei? are thei not vnneceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary &amp;
very vnprofitable things / which the word of god neuer cownceled any man to
vſe? But yet this is the worſt point in them / that men haue imagyned that
thei ſhuld obteine par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>don and remiſſyon of ſinnys rhorow ſuch
reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ques (life as thei haue imagyned of the maſſe) as though it were a
good or an high honor and ſeruice of god.</p>
               <p>Sextly. Maſſes haue bene the occaſion of pardons alſo:
which haue bene granted both to the liuing &amp; in the dead (but not for
naught with our mony) in the which pardons that fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe traiteros Iudas or
pope hath ſold the meri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes of chriſt / with the vaine or ſuperfluos
me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites <pb facs="tcp:4559:12"/>of all ſaintes / and of the whole vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal church.
wherfor thei ought in any wiſe to be condemned. for thei lacke not only the
word of god to approue them / (hauing no command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to be vſed / and being
things of no neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite) but thei are alſo cleame co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the firſt
article of the faith. for we obteine the merite of chriſt / not by our own
workes or with any mo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ny / but by faith thorow the fre grace &amp; mercy of god
with owt any mony or any merites of our own / which merite of chriſt is
offred vnto us / not by the auctorite or pour of the pope / but in the goſpel
and word of god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the inuocacyon of ſaintes.</head>
               <p>The inuocacyon of ſaintes is alſo an abuſe of Antichriſt
which repugneth with the former principal article of our redempcyon and it
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſchureth or drowneth the knoulege of chriſt.</p>
               <p>And there is no commandment / councel or example therof in the
holy ſcripture / and agai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ine although the praing vnto ſaintes were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
ſo good (as it is a very deueliſſh abuſe) yet we may receyue all things
moch better &amp; alſo more excellent / of chriſt than of any ſaint. And
not with ſtanding that the angels do pray for us in heauen (as chriſt
him<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelf alſo doth) and the ſaintes herevpon earth / and parauenture thei
that be in heauen alſo / <pb facs="tcp:4559:13"/>yet it foloweth not therupon that we
ought to inuocate / honor or pray vnto angels &amp; ſaintes or to faſt / 
kepe holy day / ſing or heare maſſes &amp; to ſacrifice or make any
oblacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the worſh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ip of any ſaint or angel / nor yet to byld any
tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ples or altars or to make any ſeruyce for them or to worſhip &amp;
ſerue them many dyuers way<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>es / to take them for patrones or defenders to
ſeke help for all maner of things of them and to byleue that eueryone of them
hath a peculy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar proper vertu by hym ſelf / ſome for one thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; ſome
for a nother as the papiſtes both teach and doo. For it is very mere Idolatry
ſo to doo for as moch as all ſuch honor is peculiarly due to god only &amp;
to no other. Thou maiſt / I wil not ſay contrary / as a chriſten man and
as a ſaint pray for me / vp on erth while thou ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt / not for one thing
/ but for all maner of things: notwithſtonding I muſt not by &amp; by / 
honor the and cal vp on theas a god / nor yet ſet vp a faſting day &amp; an
holy day in thy honor / or to ordeyne maſſes to be hard &amp; ſayd or any
other oblacyons to be done in thy honor / and ſo to put &amp; fixe all the
hope of my ſaluacyon in the there be other wayes where by I may haue the in
reuerence / loue the / reioyſe in the / and gyue the thankes in chriſt. Now
if theſe Idola<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>triſſh ſeruyce and honoriug of angels and dead ſaintes
were drowned and brought owt of me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mory / <pb facs="tcp:4559:13"/> all other honor about
them could not gretly hurt / but ſhuld daily decay. for firſt if all hope
of lucre &amp; profit were taken a way / and agayn if that the peple were
perſuaded that thei could obteine no maner of help or profyte neither
corporal nor ſpiritual / bodyly nor goſt<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly by their honoring or inuocating
of ſaintes / there wold be but fewe that wold worſhip any ſaintes whether
thei were in their graues or in heanen. For no man wold gretly remember them / 
no man wold ſerue or honor them for nawght of loue only. This is the ſomme
and effect of all together. What ſo euer is in the maſſe / what ſo euer
is ſprong vp therof / and agayn what ſo euer is annexed vnto it we can in
no wiſe ſuffer but we muſt nedes condemne them to the deuel / that we may
haue / vſe &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teine the pure &amp; certen holy ſacrament acordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to
the inſtitucyon of chriſt with true faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The third article.</head>
               <p>The colleges of prebendarys and the mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterys were at the
firſt ordeined for a good pur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſe that lerned me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and vertuos weme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> might
be brought vp in them. wherfor thei ought to be reformed / that thei were
firſt ordeined / that the church may neuer be deſtitute of lerned cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates
/ preachers and other miniſters which <pb facs="tcp:4559:14"/>may be called owt of
ſuch colleges into the co<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mon welth to be officers in cytes &amp; cownteys
Lyke wiſe of virginis wel brought vp which may after ward be vertuos matrones
and good houſe wyues. And if monaſterys and colle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges wil not conſent nor
applie themſelues to ſerue vnto theſe &amp; ſuch like vſes / it were
bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that thei were vtterly deſtroyd / ſupreſſed and ouerthrown than
that thei ſhuld be repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted more holy (than the comon ſort of chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
men and than other oyders / ſtates &amp; condici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of life inſtitute of
god him ſelfe) only for their wicked ſuperſticyons ceremonys &amp;
ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyce inuented by man for all theſe opinyons do repugne with the firſt
principal article of our redempcyon thorow Iheſus chriſt.</p>
               <p>Beſide this thei haue no commandment of god neither / no more
thn all other tradicyons and fanſys of men: thei be not neceſſary neither
nor profitable being vſed as thei be / for thei cauſe many dangeros and
perlos trobles &amp; vex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>acyons. for the prophetes them ſelues do ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue all
ſuch ſeruyce &amp; ceremonys inuented by men.</p>
               <p>Auen that is to ſay comberos things.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>The iiij Article.</head>
               <p>The pope neither is nor can be by the lawe &amp; <pb facs="tcp:4559:14"/>commandment of god the head of the whole church / for that is chriſt
alone and nome but he: And the pope is nothin els but the biſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop / curate
or pariſſh priſt of Rome and of them that of their own wil or by the
ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of man / that is to ſay by the temporal rular are appointed to be
vnder his cure / not to be ſubiect to him as to their higheſt lord &amp;
prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce / but that thei ſhuld lyke chriſten men lyue to<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gether with him
lyke brethern &amp; felows of the ſame degre / lyke as the old councels &amp;
the ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me of cypriane do euydently declare.</p>
               <p>But now there is no biſſhop in the world that dare call the
pope / brother / as thei did co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly in thoſe dayes</p>
               <p>But euen emperors &amp; kinges are fayne to call the Pope their
lord. which thing we nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil nor ought nor yet can we with a ſafe
conſcience condeſtend or grant vnto it. Who ſo erer pleaſe to do it / 
he ſhal do it alone for us. Here vp on it folo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth that all ſuch things as
the pope hath do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne / made / or ordeined / thorow his falſe / va<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yne / wicked
and vſurped tyrannical pour / ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue bene and be yet the artes and ordinances
of the very deuel / and purpoſly deuyſed to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructyon of the holy
vniuerſal Chriſten church <pb facs="tcp:4559:15"/>(ſo mach as lay in him) and to the
ouerthro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing of the firſt principal article of the redemp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of Ieſus
chriſt thoſe ordinancys only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept which concern the polytick ſtate of
the tem<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poral comon welth / wherin god giueth alſo many good &amp; holſom
thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs to the peple diuers times thorow tyrannys and godles wretchys</p>
               <p>There be papers and bulles of the pope wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in he roryth lyke a
lyon (as the angel painteth hym properly in the 12. chap. of the Apocalip.)
ſayng that no chriſten man can be ſaued exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pt he ſerue hym &amp; be
obedie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandethe / ſayeth / &amp; doth Al things
are as moch to ſay as thus / although thou byleuyſt in chriſt and haſt
obteined of hym all maner of things / yet all is to no purpoſe nor effect
except thou wilt honor me for thy god / be ſubiect to me and obey me &amp;c.
And yet it is manifeſt that the holy church had no ſuch pope or biſſhop
within theſt viij. hundreth yeares. And euen at this day the grecyans and
other nacyons be not ſubiect to no ſuch biſſhop or ſyran nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
were. Wherfor as we haue of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t
ſayd it is but a foliſſh imagyn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cyon of mans brayne / wherof ther is no commandment nor mency<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in
the holy ſcripture / and it is both an vnne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceſſary and alſo a
ſuperfluos thing / for the ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly chriſten church can ſtand with ourt any
ſuch head: and it had bene happy for the church of <pb facs="tcp:4559:15"/>god if the
deuel had neuer exalteed nor ſet vp ſuch and head. Further more the whole
pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtry / the pope with his whole rabble of car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals / biſſhapys / 
canons &amp; ſuch other / be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable &amp; ſuperfluos me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres in the
church for thei do no office pertening to a chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> man Thus the church may
well conſiſt and remayne though the pope were condemnyd to the deuel.</p>
               <p>Imagyne that the pope wold grant hymſelfe that he were not the
ſu<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>me head of the church by any lawe or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandment of god / but only
becauſe there ought to be one head in the church where vnto all other might
leane &amp; depe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that a concord &amp; vnyte might the better be kept a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mong
chriſten men againſt all ſectes and hereſys. Such an head ought to be
choſen by the conſent of all men &amp; it ou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ght to be in the lyberty and
powr of men ſenty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me to cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ſome tyme to depoſe ſuch heades lyke as
the councel of conſtance did with certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Popes: which cowncel did depoſe
iiij. popes o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne after a nother &amp; did choſe the forth. But Imagyne (I
ſay) that the pope and the court of rome wold grant thus moch (as the wil
neuer doo / for than ſhuld he be compelled to ſuffer his whole kingdome and
ordre to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerthrown and deſtroyed with all his canon lawe and al the
bokes therof / and agayn he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>not grant it for it is contrary to his oth yet
/ <pb facs="tcp:4559:16"/>I ſay / though he wold grant it / it were no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing profitable
to the church to haue any ſuch head and there ſhuld riſe by that meanes
many moo ſectes than were before / for ſeing no man were bownd to owe any
obedience to ſuch an head by the lawe and commandment of god but only euery
man to ſubmyt him ſelf vnder his ſubiecyon of his own fre wil / he
ſhuld eaſely &amp; ſone come in to contemp and be robbed or ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yled of
all his membros. fynally ſuch an head ought not to be at Rome or in any
priuate pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce but in all places and in euery church / wher ſo euer god had
geuen any ſuch and office.</p>
               <p>But oh lord what a gret confuſyon &amp; beſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe wold
this thing engender? wherfor the church can neuer be better ruled and
perſerued than if all men ſhuld lyue together vnder oue head chriſt / and
that all biſſhops (ſo moch as perteyneth to the office of a biſſhops
ſhuld be of lyke pour &amp; auctorite (alſhough thei were not lyke in
gyftes. and knoulege) and ſo conſent wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th all dilygence in vniforwe
doctrine / faith / ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cramentes / prayer / &amp; other workes of loue &amp;
charite. Thus writeth .S. Ierom that the priſtes &amp; biſſhops of the
church of Alexandria ded rule the church comonly to gether one wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>th a nother / 
lyke as the apoſtels did / and all biſſhops after ward did like wiſe in
the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſal <pb facs="tcp:4559:16"/>primatyue church vntil ſuch tyme as the po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe
began to lift vp his heade above them all. This part proueth euydently the pope
to be antichriſt / which had extolled him ſelf aboue chriſt and bent
hymſelf gainſt chriſt.</p>
               <p>He wil grant no man to be ſaued without his auctorite and pour
/ which pour not withſton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is nothing at all: neither ordeined nor
com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manded by god. What is this els than to exalt him ſelf aboue god and to
bent hym ſelfe as aduerſary againſt god as .S. Paul ſaith?</p>
               <p>The very Turck and hell it ſelf / though thei be neuer ſo
gret enmys of chriſtendome / did ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer any ſuch thing</p>
               <p>Thei permit and ſuffer all men to byleue in chriſt who ſo
wil / only thei take tributes of chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten men &amp; thei requyre all outward
obedience.</p>
               <p>But the pope forbiddeth vs to byleue in chriſt ſayng that we
muſt obey hym / and ſo we ſhal ob<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teine ſaluacyon of our ſoules.</p>
               <p>But we wil not obey hym to dye ther for / we wil rather ſubmyt
our ſelues to death in the na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of god.</p>
               <p>All this beſineſſe is ryſen hereupon that the pope wil
haue himſelf named the head of the v<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niuerſal CHRISTEN church by the lawe
of <pb facs="tcp:4559:17"/>god wherupon it muſt nedes folow that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth yea &amp;
preferreth him ſelf vnto chriſt: firſt he called hym ſelfe head of the
church: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that / lord of the church / thirdly ſupreme lord of the
vniuerſal world / and finally the god of the erth / in as moch as at length
he we<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t abo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ut to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand the angels of heauen.</p>
               <p>And if the doctrine of the pope be tryed by the the
ſcrſpture &amp; wer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pared therwith / we ſhal proue and fynd that his
doctrine euen where<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>as it if beſt / was taken out of the cyuil and
he<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>athniſſh lawe / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that it geueth lawes a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceptes of ciuyl matters
and of cyuyl iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts as his own decretals do teſtifye. After ward his
doctrine teacheth certen ceremomonys of temples / of garmentes / of choyſe of
meates / of difference betwene priſtes and lay men and of ſuch foliſſh
things / iugglyng ſoteltys and fantaſtical trifles an infinyte nomber. And
in all theſe things there is no word nor men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon of chriſt / of faith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandments of god.
Inſumma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> there is nothing in his
doctrine but deueliſſhnes / and his lyes of maſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſes / purgatory / 
monaſterys / workes and ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonys (all which be the very papiſtry) he
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tendeth to ſet aboue chriſt &amp; god and againſt god / condemnyng / 
kyllyng / and perſecuting al chriſten me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which wil not extoll &amp; honor
this his abhomynable wickedneſſe aboue all things in hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen <pb facs="tcp:4559:17"/>
and erth. for the which canſe life as we can not fynd in our hartes to bowe
to the deuel &amp; to honor him for our lord &amp; god: Euen ſo life wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe
can we not ſuffre his Apoſtle the Pope / or Antichriſt the ſupreme head
&amp; lord in his king<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dome. For to lye to murder / and te deſtroy the
ſoule with the body be the very natural pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pertys of the popys kingdome.</p>
               <p>Now the councel ſhal fynd &amp; haue inough in theſe iiij.
articles / to condemne. for thei nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can nor wil grant us the leaſt part
or po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynt of them. Of this thing we ought to dowt nothing at all / yea we
muſt rather comfort our hartes with this hope and truſt that Iheſus
chriſt wil fight againſt his emnys and perſecu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te them both with his
ſpirite and alſo with his coming which thing god grant / Amen.</p>
               <p>As for vs let us not loke that we ſhal not be ſuffred to
ſtand before the emperor or any ciuyl iudge &amp; rueler / as we did at
augſpurg where the emperor did heare our cauſe and matter fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uorably / But
we muſt ſtand before the pope and the deuel him ſelf which wil not heare
any thing at all / But with out any cauſe wil iudge us condemne us to death / 
and compel us to Idolatry whether we wil or no / wherfor we wil neuer in our
life kiſſe his fete nor ſay you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rre my good and gracios lord / but we
wil ſay (as the Angel ſait to the deuel in Zachary) god <pb facs="tcp:4559:18"/>pomiſſh the Satan / thou aduerſary of god.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="part">
            <head>The third part of the articles.</head>
            <p>Of the articles that folow it were better for us to entreat of
them with lerned and wiſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſonable men / or among our ſelues than with
the pope which with his whole ſect and faccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with hym but riches / honor / 
po<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe powr are only in reputacyon with hym.</p>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of ſinne.</head>
               <p>In this article we are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled to grant with S. Paul the v. to
the romanes / that ſinne en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred in to the world by one ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Adam / thorow
whoſe diſobedience all men are made ſinners and ſubiect to death and to
the deuel. Now the operacyons of this ſinne / are euel workes ſuch as be
forbidden in the .x. commandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / as be theſe diſtruſt in god / 
falſe faith / Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try / to be with out all feare of god / preſumpcy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on / 
deſperacyon / blyndnes of hart / and to con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>clude in a ſomme / the
ignorance and contempt of god. After theſe / to lye / to ſweare by the
na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me of not to pray / not to call vp on god / to diſpi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe or neglect the
word of god / to be diſobedient to parentes. Item murder / fleſſhly
luſt / theft &amp; falſhode. This original ſinne is ſo gret a
corrupcyon of nature / that no maner of reaſon can ſee &amp; perceiue it / 
and therfor it muſt be by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leued by the reuelacyon of the holy ſcripture / 
Pſalm. 51. Roma. v. Exodi. xxxiij. Gene. iiij.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:4559:18"/>Wherfor it is a manifeſt error and a blynd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes
repugnyng with this article / to ſay as the ſchole dyuynes or du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſys haue
taught firſt that after the fall of Adam all the natural ſtrengh of man
doth remayne perfight &amp; vncorrupt.</p>
               <p>And that man hath naturally a right reaſon and free wil / that
he may ſatiſfye &amp; fulfyll the lawe of god.</p>
               <p>Secondorly That man hath free wil ſo that he may doo all good
and eſchewe all euel. &amp; agayne on the contrary part / leaue that which is
good and fo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>low the euel.</p>
               <p>Thirdly That a man by the proper ſtrengthe of his own nature
may ſatiſfye and fulfill the whole lawe of god.</p>
               <p>Fortly That a man of his own natural ſtrenth can loue god
aboue all thing / and his neihbor as him ſelfe.</p>
               <p>Fiftly That if a man do &amp; performe ſo moch as he is able
to doo / than ſhal he ſurely obteine gods fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uor.</p>
               <p>Sextly. That it is not neceſſary for him that wil receyue
the ſacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment / <pb facs="tcp:4559:19"/>to haue a purpoſe to lyue wel afterward.</p>
               <p>But that it is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ufficient if he haue not an ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynate and wicked purprſe to
ſinne: ſo good is our nature of it ſelf / and ſo ſuch efficacyte is
the vertu of the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rament.</p>
               <p>Seuently. That it is not taught in the ſcripture that it is
neceſſary for him that wil do any good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke / to haue the holy goſt
with his grace.</p>
               <p>Theſe &amp; ſuch like errors haue ſprong vp of blindnes
and ignorance / becauſe thei were ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant both of ſinne / &amp; alſo of
chriſt our ſauy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or: and thei be very heathniſſh opinyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s which we can
not ſuffer nor abyde. for if thei were tue tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did chriſt dye in vaine / 
for as moch as ther is no corrupcyon nor ſinne in man (after their o<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pynyon)
for the which chriſt nedyd to haue dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. Or els he muſt haue dyed for the
body only &amp; not for the ſowle / for the ſowle is vncorrupt and the body
only ſubiect to death after this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pynyon.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the lawe.</head>
               <p>In this article our iudgement is that the la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we was geuen by god
to bridle &amp; refrayne us fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſinnyng partly with threatni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs and with
feare of poniſſhment / partly with promiſes of grace / fauor and other
benifites: But all the<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe do help but litle by reaſon of the corrupcyon and
wickednes which ſinne doth engender in <pb facs="tcp:4559:19"/>man for hereby ſome
which are emnys of the la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we are made worſe: for as moch as thei deſyre
more feruently to doo ſuch thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs as thei are for<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bidden to do by the lawe / 
and thei do not gladly ſuch things as thei are commanded to do.</p>
               <p>And thus in as moch as thei are feared by po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſhment / 
thei offend now ſtil more againſt the lawe than thei ded before. Now ſuch
are vnrecouerable and damnable, perſons paſt all amendment for thei commit
ſinne &amp; wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes as oft as any occaſyon of ſinning is nffred.</p>
               <p>There be other ſome / which are blynd / and bo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aſt &amp;
extolle the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues / ſuppoſing that thei can ſaue them ſelues thorow
their own pour &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ght / thinking them ſelues able to kepe And
per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>forme the lawe as is before ſaid of the ſchole dyuynes or Sunſes. And
by ſuch meanes / be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>come thei hypocrites and only colored ſaintes / holy
outwardly only.</p>
               <p>But the chefe office &amp; effect of the lawe is this / to
ſhewe and declare original ſinne: a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d to teach man how ſore his nature is
infect or poi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſoned / And that it is altogether corrupt / vnto whom the lawe
ſaith that he honoreth not god but contemneth him &amp; honoreth ſtrange
falſe goddes which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before the lawe taught him it / he did in no wiſe
bileue it to be true. Now man being put in feare humbleth him ſelf / 
ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iecteth and abateth his hart and vtterly deſpa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ireth / <pb facs="tcp:4559:20"/>and
deſiereth feruently to haue ſome help and bei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g diſmazed that he can not
tel whether to turn him / he beginneth to be a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gry with god and to murmur
againſt him: And this it is that is ſpoken in the iij. to the romanes / The
la<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>we worketh wrath: &amp; againe in the v. to the ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>manes / the lawe entred
in / that ſinne ſhuld be more abundant.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of penance.</head>
               <p>This office and work of the lawe is kept &amp; re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>teined in the
newe teſtament / and it is alſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed as .S. Paul ſaith the .i. to
the roma ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the wrath of god from heauen is declared mamifeſtly
againſt all wickednes and vnright wiſnes of men. Item the iij. to the Roma.
the whole world is gilty to god. Item no fleſſh ſhal be iuſtifyed in
his ſight by the workes of the lawe. Item Iohan the xvi. The holy goſt
ſhal reproue the world of ſinne. This is the tho<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>der of god wherby he doth
ouerthrowe and cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rely conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne not only manifeſt ſinners but eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
hypocrytes alſo / and he bringeth them in to fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ar and deſperacyon / This
is the hammer wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of Ieremy ſpeketh ſaing / My word is an han<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mer that
beateth flynt ſtonys in to pouder.</p>
               <p>This is no actyue or procured contricyon but it is a paſſyne
or a ſuffring contricyon and bre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aking / for it is a tru or erneſt
heuyneſſe of the <pb facs="tcp:4559:20"/>hart / a very paſſyon / felyng vnd taſt
of death.</p>
               <p>And this is to begynne a repentance or a newe life and man is
compelled to heare ſuch a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence as this: Ye are all condemned and
confo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unded / whether ye be open ſinners or hypocry<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes / ye muſt alter
your lyues and be newe men. And ye muſt lyue other wiſe than ye lyue now.
For how gret / wiſe / mighty &amp; holy ſo euer ye be / yet there is none
of yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> iuſt &amp;c. But now vnto
this office and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demnacion of the lawe / the newe teſtament bringeth a
comfortable pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mes of grace and mercy thorow the goſpel / wh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ich ꝓmes
we ought to receiue by faith as chriſt ſaith March the .i. So penance and
byleue the goſpel: that is to ſay / turne amend and lyue bet<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter and byleue
my promes. And before chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtes coming Iohan was called the preacher of
penance / but yet vnto the remiſſyon of ſinnes: that is to ſay / it was
Iohans office to repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue all men and to teach them that thei all were
ſinners / that thei might knnoch what maner of men thei were before god and
grant themſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to be damnable ſinners. that ſo thei might be prepared
to the lord to embrace his and mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy for their comfort / and to byleue and
truſt to receiue remiſſyon of their ſinnes of chriſt.</p>
               <p>And ſo ſaith Chriſt him ſelfe in the laſt chap. of
Luke / penance and remiſſion of ſinnes <pb facs="tcp:4559:21"/>muſt be preached in
my name among all naci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. Now if the lawe ſhuld doo his offyce fre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly alone
and the goſpel remoued / we ſhuld ſe no<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thing but deth and hell redy to
deuoure us / and there were no remedy but all men ſhuld be compelled to
deſpayre as Saul &amp; Iudas did / lyke as .S. Paul ſaith: The lawe thorow
ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne doth kil. But the goſpel again / bringeth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fort &amp;
remiſſyon of ſinnes / not one way only but dyuers / as thorow the word of
god / tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row the ſacramentes &amp; ſuch other ways (as we ſhal heare
here after) that thorow him we may haur a plentuos and a rich redempcyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (as
the cxxx. Pſalme ſaith) againſt the gret capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyte and thraldom of
ſinne. But we muſt now compare the falſe penance of the popiſſh
dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes &amp; ſophiſters. With the true penance that thei both may the
better be known.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the falſe penance of the papiſtes</head>
               <p>It was impoſſible that euer the papiſtes ſhuld teach
&amp; preach truly of penance / ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thei vnderſtode not
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>inne truly. For / as is before
ſayd / thei haue no right iudgement or knoule<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ge of original ſinne / but
thei teach that the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural ſtrength of man hath euer remayned per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fight / 
pure &amp; vncorrupt / that mans reaſon ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> teach rightly. And that his wil
can perfihhtly obey this right reaſon / a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d again that god doth ſurely gyue
his grace and mercy whan a man <pb facs="tcp:4559:21"/>doth o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſo moch as he is able
to do by his own fre wil. Wherfor it muſt nedes folowe that thei did penance
&amp; repent only for actual ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. for the corrupt affeccyons of the hart
/ as luſt and concupiſcens are no ſinnes with them but thei repute
thoſe only for ſinnes / which be outward &amp; actual workes ſpringing of
their fre wil. And of this penance thei haue made. 3. partes / Contricyon / 
Confeſſion &amp; Satiſfacci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with this comfort &amp; promes annexed
the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runto that if a man ſhuld do true penance / con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>feſſe himſelf
per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>y and make true ſati<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon / than <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d he meryte &amp; de<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erue remiſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his ſinnes and
make a perfite ſatiſfaccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on beford god for all his ſinnes. Thus in
the<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ir penance thei taught me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to truſt in their own workes. And hereupon
ſpra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g vp that which thei vſe to blowe out in the pulpets as oft as thei
make mencyon of the comon confeſſyon to the peple ſaing O lord god kepe
&amp; pre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erue my life vntil I haue
done pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for my ſinnes and amended my life. Here is neuer a word of
chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſt nor of faith but euery man bileueth to wipe a way and diſpatch his
ſinnes before god thorov his own workes. And for this purpoſe haue many
made them felues priſtes and monkes that thei might ſo reſiſt and
witſtond ſinne.</p>
               <p>As for contricyon this hath euer bene the ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ner &amp; order
therof. for as moch as no man co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uld <pb facs="tcp:4559:22"/>remember all his ſinnes
particularly (ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ally all and euery one that he had committed the whole
yeare / ) thus thei trifled and dalyd ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with / that if any ſecret &amp;
preuy ſinnes ſhuld af<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>terward come to his rememberance / he muſt do
penance alſo for them &amp; teherſe them at his next confeſſyon / and
in the meane time thei we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re committed to the grace and mercy of god
fur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thermore becauſe no man could tel certe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly how gret his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tricyon ought
to be wherby he migh fully ſatiſfye god / thei addet this comfort to the
peple that he which could not haue perfight contricyon / ſhuld labor at leaft
to haue attricy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on / which I may call an half contricyon or a li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tel ſpice of
contricyon / for as for thei them ſel<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ues vnderſtode neither the one nor
the other a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d thei knowe no more what theſe wordes contri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon and attrieyon
do ſignifye than I do.</p>
               <p>Now this attricyon (as thei call it) was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted ſufficyent
for contricyon / whan ſo euer thei were confeſſed. And if it chanſed at
any ti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>me that ſome man ſhuld ſay in his confeſſion that he could not
haue perfite coutricyon or that he could not lament mourne and be fory for his
ſinnes (which thing myght happen in ſuch as were taken and rauiſſhed
with the loue of ſome harlot or in ſuch as did burne with deſire to be
reuenged of their emnys &amp; cetera) than thei to <pb facs="tcp:4559:22"/>vſed to axe
ſuch whether he deſiered to haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tricyon / or no. If he anſwered / 
Yea / (for who wold ſay May / except it were the deuel himſelf?) than thei
toke that as ſufficient for contricyon / and thei forgaue him his ſinnes
and aſſoiled him euen for that vertu and good worke: alledging for them the
example of .S. Bernard &amp; cet.</p>
               <p>Now by this we ſee how blynd mans reaſon is and how it
ſtombleth in matters of faith a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſeketh comfort at hir own pleſure in
hir own proper ſtrength / and can not ones thinke nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of CHRIST nor yet
of faith.</p>
               <p>Now wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the matter is brought in to light and ſene / This
contrityon is nothing els than a fained and falſe prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſed imaginacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
ſprong vp out of the proper ſtrength of man both with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out faith a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d alſo
without any knoulege of chriſt in the which contrityon the pore ſimple
ſinner wold haue laughed many tymes rather tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue wept / ſpecially whan
his luſt and deſyre of reuengeance againſt his emny hath comne to his
mynd and remembera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: thoſe only except whom either the lawe hath thorouly
feared or els whom the deuel hath vexed and turmoyled with heuynes of hart. Els
/ I ſay / their contricyon was nothing els than a very right hipocriſy / 
and it neuer abated or <pb facs="tcp:4559:23"/>mortifyed the luſt of ſinne for men
were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to contricion / whan as thei had rather haue ſinned more if
thei might. And as for the maner of their confeſſyon this it was / Eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ry
man was compelled to nomber all his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes (which was an impoſſible
thing) And this was an abhomynable tiranny. But ſuch things as he had
forgoten / he was aſſoiled of them and thei were forgeuen him on this
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>yon that afterward whan thei
came to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he ſhuld
confeſſe them. And by this me<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
a man could neuer be ſure whan he were
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> confeſſed or whan his
confeſſyon ſhuld <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> an end
And yet notwithſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding thei bad him put his truſt in his worke and
diligence: for thei ſayd that the more purely he were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed / and
the more that he were aſhamed and had diſpraiſed him ſelf before the
priſt ſo moch the ſoner and better ſhuld he ſatiſfye and make
ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dys for his ſinnes / becauſe ſuch an hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling did merite or
deſerue grace / fauor &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy before god. Neither was here alſo any
mencyon of chriſt. And agayn the ſtrength &amp; ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tu of abſolucyon was
not taught nor declared to the penitent neither. And thus all his co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort did
conſiſt in the nombring vp of his ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his ſhamefaſtnes But no man can expreſſe with
wordes / what heuynes or ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row / what abhominacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> and filthines / what 
<pb facs="tcp:4559:23"/>Idolatry and ſuperſticyon haue grown of this confeſſyon.
Finally ſatiſfaccyon is large in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ough for there was no man in the world
that euer could knouwe how moch he ought to doo or ſatiſfye for one ſinne
only / how ſhuld he tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> knowe how moch to doo for all his ſinnes?</p>
               <p>But thei imagined and found out a prety di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uyſe / that the
priſtes ſhuld enioyne their peni<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tentys certen ſatiſſaceyons (which
thei named penance) ſuch as might eaſely be kept and performed as theſe.
v. pater noſters and to faſt a day or .ij. &amp; ſuch lyke / and the
reſidue of their penance thei referred to purgatory there to be fully
performed. Was not this now a very miſery and a heuy calamyte alſo? There
were ſome that ſuppoſed &amp; byleued that thei ſhuld neuer go owt of
purgatory becauſe after the old canons / one deadly ſinne requireth .vij.
yea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res of penance. And ſtyl thei put truſt in their own workes of
ſatiſfaccyon. And if their ſatiſfaction could haue bene a ſufficient
&amp; per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fight fatiſfaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> than might all hope and truſt of ſaluacyon
haue bene put altogether in ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faccyon / in ſo moch that we ſhuld
haue had no neade neither of faith nor yet of chriſt. But it was
impoſſible to haue ſuch a ſatiſfaccyon.</p>
               <p>Now if any man had done penance after this faſſhon euen for
the ſpace of an hundreth yeare yet he ſhuld neuer haue known whan he had
do<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ne <pb facs="tcp:4559:24"/>and performed perfight or ſufficient penan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce. And this
were nothing els than alweys to do penance and yet neuer to come vnto penan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce.
And herein did the court of rome help pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tily to ſucker the miſerable
church / and imagy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned pardos wherby he did remitt penance and brought
ſatiſfaccyon inough / firſt particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for viij. yeares / an hundreth
yeares &amp; cete.</p>
               <p>And he d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>yded them by
lompes among car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals and biſſhapes / that ſome ſhuld haue auc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torite
to grant an .C. yeares / ſome an C. Day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of pardon.</p>
               <p>But he reſerued to him ſelf alone to remitt and pardon the
whole penance or ſatiſfaccy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. This thing whan it began to ſmack wel and
to bring lucre to the purſe / and again for as moch as the marchan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>diſe and
ſelling of bullys did proſpere and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cede wel and luckyly / he imagyned a
Goldyn ye<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>are or a yeare of gre which he wold haue no where but at Rome / and
this yeare ful remiſſyon of all penaltys / pomiſſhments / penance and
all maner of ſinnes / and thether ran all men from all partes of the world to
fet pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the goldyn yeare. But who wold not haue deſyered to haue bene
deliuered from ſuch an heuy &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tollerable burden? This was euen as moch
as to find &amp; exalt all the treſures of the erth. But the pope continewed
daily in heaping many gol<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyn <pb facs="tcp:4559:24"/>yeares together one vp on another.
And the more mony he deuoured / the gretter waxed his throte. And thus at
length he ſent his gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyn yeare in to other nacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s by his legatys eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> tyl
all churches &amp; houſes were filled &amp; ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed with goldyn yeares
fynally he braſt into purgatory at length alſo to the deade ſowlys
firſt thorow Maſſes / Commendacyons / foun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dacyons &amp; at laſt thorow
his pardons &amp; his goldyn yeare. What nede I to make many wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des? Soules
were ſo good cheape that a man might bye as many as he wold for ij. pens or a
grote the pece. And yet all this was not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ent neither for the pope
although he taught &amp; commanded men to put all their truſt of ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyon
in his pardons / yet not with ſtonding he made this way dout ful &amp;
vncerten alſo. for he wrote thus in his bullys that who ſo euer wold be
partaker of his pardon &amp; of his goldyn yea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re he muſt both doo penance
for all his ſinnes and confeſſe them &amp; alſo pay ſome mony. But we
haue ſayd before that the popiſſh contricy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and confeſſion alſo
is both doutful / vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and alſo very hypocriſy. And beſide this / no
man did know what ſoule was in purgato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry / and if there were any yet it was
vnknowne which had true contricyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; was rightly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſed &amp; which
not. Here the pope toke mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>y &amp; bad them truſt in his penance &amp;
pardons &amp; yet not with <pb facs="tcp:4559:25"/>ſtonding he ſent them agayn to
their own do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>utful &amp; vncerten workes. Now if there were any / which thought
them ſelues free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all ac<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tual ſinnes / euel affeccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / wicked wordes
&amp; dedes / thei wold make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes / fry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res &amp; priſtes in
monaſterys / collegys and felou<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſhips &amp; thei wold reſiſt euel
deſyres / with fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting / watchi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g at midnight / prayer / ſayng of
maſſes / hard clothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g and hard lodgi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; thus they went about to be
ſaued by force &amp; violence whether god wold or no. But yet the original or
byrth ſinne that was in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> did ſometime pa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>raue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ture exerciſe his
ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght while thei were a ſlepe / as .S. Auſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; .S. Bierom with
other do gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. And yet theſe did think &amp; iudge amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues that
there were ſome ſo holy (as thei alſo taught) that thei were with out all
ſinne, ful of god workes / in ſo moch that thorow this ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe &amp; truſt
thei delt &amp; ſold vnto other me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> their good workes which were
ſuꝑfluos for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ues to right wiſnes. This is true / for the
ſea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>les / writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs &amp; tokens therof be yet to ſhewe. Such had no nede of
pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cc them ſelues. for how could thei repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for any ſinne wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thei
ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented to any wicked cogitacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s or thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghtes? And again what
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> could thei ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke ſeing thei eſchewed to ſpeake one to
another / for thei were ſworn to ſyle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce: And finally for what thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
ſhuld thei make ſatiſfaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſei<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thei <pb facs="tcp:4559:25"/>were gilty of no
ſinnes? Euen ſuch ſaintes were the phariſes &amp; ſcrybes in
chriſtes tyme: But than immediatly came the fyery Angel &amp; meſſenger
S. Iohan / the preacher of true penance &amp; ſtroke them both at one clap
&amp; with one thonder bolt / ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing / do penance. Now the one ſort of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
though thus / we haue done penance al ready? And the other thought thus / we
nede not do any penance But .S. Iohan ſaith to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both doo pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce both ij.
of yow haue euer yet done any true penance in your life dayes / but ye be
hypocrytes and both of yow haue nede of remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſines becouſe ye
both be ignorant / as yet / what ſinne is properly / moch leſſe can yow
either do any pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce for your ſinne / or els auoyde ſinne. There is none
of yow good / ye be all ful of vnfaithfulnes / of blyndnes of the ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce
both of god &amp; of his wil alſo But now is he preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of whoſe ple<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ty
we all muſt receiue gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce for grace and with out hym can no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be
iuſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fyed before god. Wherfor if ye wil do pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / do it rightly &amp;
truly. for your pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce which haue ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de of no pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce / ye generacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of
ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes / who haue told yow that ye might auoide the wrath &amp; damnacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
to come? &amp;c: S. Paul alſo preacheth li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke wiſe to the romanes in the
.iij. chapter / ſaing.</p>
               <p>There is none that hath any knoulege / there is none that
ſeketh god there is none that doth god no not one: All are beconne
vnprofitable &amp; haue ſwarued out of the right way. And agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the 16 
<pb facs="tcp:4559:26"/>of the actes. Now doth god preach vnto all men that all ſhuld
ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d their lyues. Marke: he ſait / all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / none except / that is a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
This penance which Iohan &amp; Paul do preach / teacheth us to knoulege our
ſinne / &amp; to grant that we are all da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ned of our own nature / that there
is no goodnes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> us / &amp; that we muſt nedys be renewed / altered &amp;
made newe me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. This pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is not unperfight / as is that which is done for
actual ſinnes only. Neither is it doutful or incerte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as that is for it
di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſputeth not which is ſinne &amp; chhich is not ſinne / but it
conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neth all to gether &amp; ſaith there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in yow but ſinne.
What nede we tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to make any nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brynh / differe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce or diuyſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: Wherfor
this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tricyon alſo is no vncerte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g. for there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g left in us
by this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tricyon wherby we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo moch as thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k any thing that is good wher
with we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſatifye &amp; make a me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>des for our ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes but o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ly very bare
&amp; manifeſt deſꝑacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of all thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs wh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ich we know / thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>k
ſpeake or doo. Lykewiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſyon after this maner ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be falſe
/ vncerte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfight. for who ſo euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth that there is no
thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in him but ſinne he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth all maner of ſinnes &amp; leaueth / 
excludeth or forgetteth none: fi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nally ſuch a ſatiſfaccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not be
vncerte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> neither. for it is not our vncerte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vnpure worke / but it is the
paſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; blode of the pure innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t lambe of god which taketh a way
the ſinnes of the world. Of this pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce did .S. Iohn &amp; after ward
chriſt <pb facs="tcp:4559:26"/>himſelf in the goſpel / preach: And of ſuch a
pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce do we preach alſo. And by this penance do we refuſe the pope &amp;
all things what ſo euer is byl<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded vp our own workes. for all ſuch things
ſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d vp on an vncleane / feble yea &amp; a vayne fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a vayne work or
lawe / be it neuer ſo good: for we<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>aknes / infirmyte &amp; imꝑfeccyon
remayneth in all god workes &amp; no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fulfilleth the lawe (as chriſt
ſaith Ioh. the 8.) but all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſgreſſe it. Wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>for this bildyng
is nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g but lying / falſhode &amp; hi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pocriſy eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is moſt
holy &amp; ſheweth beſt of all. But the pena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that we ſpeke of / 
endureth wi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>th all chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> til their death / &amp; it fighteth with
the re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nantes of ſinne which remayne in the fleſſh / as long as thei lyue
/ as .S. Paul witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the 7. to the Romanes ſaing that he him ſelf
warreth againſt the laue of his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres / &amp; that not with his own
ꝓper pour or ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth / but with the gift &amp; grace of the holy
goſt which euer cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nyth &amp; goeth together with remiſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of
ſinnes. This grace pourgeth &amp; dryueth out dayly the re<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts of ſinne
&amp; it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tendeth or laboreth to make ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſt pure &amp; holy. Of this
doctrine is the pope with his dyuynes / du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſes / lawyres &amp; ſuch other / 
as ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t as an aſſe for this doctryne is reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyd &amp; geue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
heauen thorow the goſpel / and yet it is caled hereſy of the wicked
pharyſys and po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pe holy hipocrites. And again on the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary part there be
ſome brayneles dotrels ſuch as were <pb facs="tcp:4559:27"/>in the tyme of ſedicyon
before my dayes / and be to fynd parauenture eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at this day alſo) which
iud<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ge and think that all thoſe which haue ones recey<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ued the holy goſt / 
their ſinnes / &amp; were ones ma<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>de faith ful / that if thei falle &amp;
offend afterward / yet thei remayne in faith / and that ſinne can not hurt or
hinder them: And thei blaſe and crye doo what thou wilt / if thou byleuyſt,
it maketh no mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter / for faith wipeth a way all thy ſinnes. And thei adde
this more ouer alſo / that who ſo euer fal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leth or ſinneth after he is
ones iuſtifyed / had ne<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uer the holy goſt perfightly / nor yet true
faith.</p>
               <p>Such doting mer chantes haue I hard many ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes / &amp; I feare
leſſe there be ſome yet which are ſtyll poſſeſſed with this
deuel or with ſuch a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. Wherfore it muſt be taught &amp; known that
both faith &amp; the holy goſt are abſent from all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo euer thei
fall into any manifeſt ſinne / as Dauyd whan he did fall into adultery / 
murder / &amp; blaſphemy of god / beſydes that thei haue &amp; fe<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>le ſtil
their original or birth ſinne &amp; fight aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inſt it dayly alſo with all
their penance. For wher ſo euer the holy goſt is / he wil not ſuffer
ſinne to exercyſe his ſtrength or to preuayle ſo far that it be
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted / but the holy goſt refrainet / brydleth &amp; forbiddeth him to
doo thvt thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g which he wold doo: And if he do or commit it / than is he
deſtitu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te of the holy goſt &amp; of faith alſo. For .S. Iohan ſaith
that who ſo euer is borne of god co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitteth <pb facs="tcp:4559:27"/>no ſinne nor ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
not ſinne / &amp; yet notwitſto<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding it is true that he ſaith afterward / 
that if we ſay we haue no ſi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne / we lye &amp; the truth of god is not i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
vs</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the goſpel.</head>
               <p>Now wil we come to the goſpel which bri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth councel &amp;
help againſt ſinne / moo ways tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one for god is vnmeſurably liberal i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
his grace &amp; mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy. firſt thorow the outward word wherby is pre<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>a ched
&amp; promiſed remiſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes thorowt the whole world / which is
the peculyar &amp; proper of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the goſpel. Secondarly thorow
Baptyme.</p>
               <p>Thirdly thorow the ſupper of the lord: Forthly thorow the pour
of the keys &amp; thorow the brother<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacyon &amp; comfort of the
faithful one to a nother among them ſelues mathew the xviij. Wher ſo euer
ij. or .iij. be gathered in my name &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of baptyme</head>
               <p>Baptyme is nothing els than the word with the dippyng in to the
water after the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of god. or / as Paul ſaith it is a waſſhing / 
to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the word / like as S. Auſten alſo affir<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>meth &amp; ſaith:
let the word come or be ioyned vnto the element / &amp; than is a ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.
Wherfor we conſent not with S. Thomas nor with the blacke fryers which
forgetting chriſtes inſtitucyon / do teach &amp; hold that god did indue
the water with a ſpiritual or goſtly pour &amp; vertu / which pour &amp;
vertu doth waſſh a way ſi<seg rend="decorInit">n</seg>es eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thorow the wa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ter. Neither do we agree
vnto du<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s nor the gray <pb facs="tcp:4559:28"/>frires / which ſpeake neuer a word of the
miniſtra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cyon of it nor of faith nor yet teach that the holy goſt is geuen
thorow the word &amp; the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes to gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the baptyme of infantys.</head>
               <p>We think that yong infantys ought to be bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed becauſe
thei perteine to the redempcyon that is promiſed to mankynd thorow chriſt.
And the church / that is to ſay the faithful congregacyon / ought to offer
them vnto chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the ſacrament of the body &amp; blode of chriſt</head>
               <p>We iudge and think that vnder breade &amp; wyue in the ſupper
of the lord are geuen the true body &amp; blode of chriſt. Item that the
whole ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ought to be miniſtred to the lay peple
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> not only one part ther of for we
haue no nede of that high lerning &amp; wiſdom which teacheth that as moch is
conteined vnder one kynd as is vnder both / as the ſophiſtical &amp;
popiſſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> phariſes and the
cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cel of conſtance do ttach. And though it were true / that as moch were
conteinet vnder one kynd as the ſophiſtical papiſtes ſay / yet the one
kynd alo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne / is not the hole inſtitucyon &amp; ordinance ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen commanded us
of Chriſt. And ſpecially we condemne excom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>icate and curſe / in the name of god / not only them which wil not
receiue both kyndes / but them pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipally which do lordly / vio and
tyrannoſly forbid / conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne and reproue it as hereſy / For as moch as in
ſo ding thei ſet and bend them ſelues againſt chriſt our lord and 
<pb facs="tcp:4559:28"/>god / ye &amp; preferre them ſelues alſo before &amp; ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oue
him. As for the tranſſubſtanciacyon / that is to ſay / that the bread
&amp; wyne in the ſupper ſhuld loſe their natural ſubſtance and only
that the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milytude forme &amp; color of bread ſhuld remayne &amp; not
very true breade / we paſſe not vp on the ſut<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tel iuglyng imagynacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of
the phariſes. For it is very conformable vnto the holy ſcripture that there
ſhuld be &amp; remayne ſtill / very breade as. S Paul him ſelf nameth it
/ ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / The breade which we breake &amp;c. Item / and ſo let him eate of
the breade &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the keys of the church</head>
               <p>The keys are the office &amp; pour of the whole chu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rch or
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gregacyon geuen of chriſt to bynd &amp; tv lo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſe ſinnes not only
manifeſt / open &amp; know ſinnes / but euen preuy ſinnys alſo / which
god only doth knowe. for as it is written / who knoweth how moch he ſinneth?
&amp; Paul hym ſelf in the 7. to the romanes complaineth that he ſerueth
and obeyth the lawe of ſinne after his fleſſh. For it is not in our pour
/ but in gods only to iudge which be ſin<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / how ſore &amp; greuos all
ſinnes are and how manyſinnes we haue / as it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / Entre not into
iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t with thy ſeruact / for no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> lyu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yng ſhal be rightuos in thi
ſight. &amp; Paul the i. to the corynth. the iiij. chap. ſaith I know my
ſelfe gilty of nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g but yet I am not therfor iuſtifyed or rightuos.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <pb facs="tcp:4559:29"/>
               <head>Of confeſſyon or abſolucyon</head>
               <p>For as moch as abſolucyon / or the pour of the keys
inſtitute or ordeyned in the goſpel by chriſt doth bring gret co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort to
weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcye<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cys agai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſt ſinne / it ought not to be vtterly
baniſſhed out of the church for .ij. cauſes ſpecially. Firſt for
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of feble / fera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ul &amp;
weake co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cys. Seco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>darly that wild &amp; reckles youth might be examyned
/ ex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ercyſed &amp; inſtruct in the doctrine &amp; knoulege of chriſt. But
as for the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bring vp of ſinnes ought to be in euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s liberty to no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber
&amp; tell o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly ſuch as he wil him ſelf without any maner of co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pulſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on.
For as long as we remaine in this fleſſh / we ſhal not lye at all if
euery one of us ſay thus: I am a wretched and a miſerable creature ful of
ſinnes &amp; as .S. Paul ſaith / Roma vij. I feele a nother lawe in my
fleſſh &amp; me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bres rebelling aga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>inſt the lawe of my mynd &amp;c. And
for as moch as priuate abſolucyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cometh fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the powr of the ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ys / it
ought not to be conte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ned but to be moch re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded as all other offices
perteining to the chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſten church ought to be. And in ſuch things as
ꝑ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine to the outward word / it muſt be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtantly holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;
bileued that god geueth his ſpirite or gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ce to no man except the outward
word either co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me betwene or els goo before. This muſt be bile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued / 
leſſe we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>all in to the errors
of thorite of god by a certen inward inſpiracion without the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de alſo
before thei euer thei hard of the word: and fret <pb facs="tcp:4559:29"/>after ward vp on
this perſuaſion thei wil take vp on the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to iudge / i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ter<g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>te / wreſt
&amp; writhe the ſcri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pture at their own pleaſure / as one Monetarius did / 
&amp; I feare there be many at this time that doo likewiſe / which wold be
quick &amp; erneſt iudges betwene the ſpirite &amp; the letter / &amp; yet
thei know not what to ſay nor what to teach. &amp; the papiſtry is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g els tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> drowned in this hereſy &amp; poſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeſſed with this
ſpirite: for the pope boſteth hym<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſelfe to haue all maner of lawes i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his
own boſom &amp; euen vnder his girdel / &amp; that what ſo euer he with his
church doth iudge / determine &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that muſt nedes be of the holy
goſt / &amp; iuſt or lau<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful / although it be clene co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to the
ſcripture or to the outward word. &amp; this is eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the old Sata<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;
ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which entyſed &amp; brought Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; Eue in to the ſelf ſame
hereſy / &amp; he drewe hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cleane a way fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the outward word vnto a certen
ſpu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>alnes &amp; vnto his own fanſys or imaginacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s &amp; yet the deuel
wrought this matter by other outward wo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>des / like as our heretikes alſo do
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward word &amp; yet thei the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues hold not their tu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ges
but fill the whole world with their babli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g clattri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / &amp; writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g: as
though the ſpirite could not come thorow the outward word of god but o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly
thorow their writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs &amp; their wordes &amp; whi- do thei not leaue their
preachi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g alſo tyl that ſpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>te
of theirs vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with out their writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g &amp; befo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re their writi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / as thei
boſt that it came vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:4559:30"/>with out any preaching of the
ſcripture? But it is no tyme now to ſpeake more largely of them.</p>
               <p>I haue entreated ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly of them in other pla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ces. And
euen thei which byleue before thei be ba<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ptiſed or which receiue faith at
their baptyme / thei haue it thorow the outward word going be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore / as thei
which be of perfight age &amp; haue any vnderſtanding muſt nedes haue hard
before this worde / Who ſo euer bileueth &amp; is baptized ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>be ſaued:
al though at the firſt thei were infidels &amp; receiued both the holy goſt
&amp; baptime alſo eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> x. yeare after. &amp; Cornelius in the x. of the
actes had hard long before amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the Iewes that chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſte &amp; meſſias
ſhuld come thorow whom he was iuſt before god / &amp; his prayers &amp;
almes were ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable thorow his faith / as luke callleth hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> iuſt faitful
&amp; vertuos. And ſurely he could neuer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue bileued truly nor yet haue
bene iuſtified with<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>out the word or without the hearing of it. And therfor it
was neceſſacy for S. Peter to reuele &amp; ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto him that the
Meſſias (in whom not yet reueled he had byleued vntil that time) was now
come that he ſhuld not bileue ſtil with the vnfath<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ful &amp; blind Iewes
that chriſt was yet to come / but rather that he ſhuld knowe that he muſt
ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>laſti<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſaluacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
thorow the meſſyas that was come &amp; already preſent &amp; that he
ſhuld not denye / &amp; perſecute this meſſias / as the Iewes did. But
to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>clude the effect of the matter brefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <pb facs="tcp:4559:30"/>this hereſy
ſowne in Ada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; his childern or po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſterite fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the begi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming vntil the
e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the world thorow the old ſerpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; drago<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / is the original
be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tayn / ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght / &amp; pour of all hereſy / of all
papiſtry &amp; of all Mahometes doctrine alſo. Wherfor / I ſay we muſt
determine this pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly / that god worketh with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> no notherwiſe tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
thorow his outward word &amp; ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t &amp; what ſo euer me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> blowe &amp;
blaſe of the ſpirite with out this outward word &amp; this facrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / it
is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g els tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the very deuel god wold not firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>peare &amp; ſhewe
hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelfe vnto moiſes / but thorow the fyery / red / &amp; vocal word. And
Iohan baptiſt was neither co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ceiued withoue the word of gabri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el goi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before
/ neither did he leape i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his mothers womb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> without the voice of mary goi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g before. &amp; S. Peter
ſaith that the prophetes did not ꝓpheci thorow the wil of ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / but
thorow the holy goſt / for thei were holy me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp;c. but yet thei were not
ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly with out the outward word / moch leſſe wold the holy goſt haue
moued the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to haue ꝓphecyed if thei had bene as yet prophane &amp; wholy.
For thei were holy / ſaith he / whan the holy goſt did ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ke thorow
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacyon</head>
               <p>As for the gret exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>municacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as the pape calleh it / we take
it o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly for a ciuil pomiſſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t / &amp; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>for it ꝑteineth nothi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g
vnto us which be eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cal miniſters. But the true &amp; right
chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municacion wherby manifeſt open and obſtinate<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er 
<pb facs="tcp:4559:31"/>comon ordina<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of the church &amp; oth vntil thei repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d
&amp; forſake their ſinnes / ꝑteineth vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>to us / &amp; preachers
ought not to ioyne the ciuil po<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to this ſpiritual
pomiſhme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of geui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of ordres &amp; of the calli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of
miniſters</head>
               <p>If biſſhops wold be right biſſhops &amp; take cure of
the church &amp; of the goſpel / tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for charites &amp; for vnites ſake / 
we wold permit the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (but not as it were a neceſſary article of the faith)
to ordeine / admit &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>firme all miniſters &amp; preachers / ſo that
all foliſſhnes / charmi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g / co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuring &amp; all ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of wicked ceremonys
were remoued and ſet a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>part. But now for as moch as thei be not nor wil not
be right true biſſhops but rather te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poral &amp; ci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uil lordes &amp; rulers
/ &amp; wil neither teach / preach baptize miniſter the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes nor do
any other worck or office that ꝑteineth to the church but on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly
perſecute &amp; conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ne ſuch as ſerue &amp; miniſter truly in the
church acordi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g to their vocacio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / the church ought not to
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e deſtitute of true miniſters
&amp; therfor as the old exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ples of the church in fore time &amp; of the old
fathers alſo do teach us / we wil &amp; be bownd our ſelues to ordeine apt
&amp; mete par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſons for ſuch offices which thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g thei ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not denye nor
forbid us to do eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by their own lawe. For their own lawes do ſay &amp;
affirme plai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly that ſuch as be ordeined &amp; admitted to the office of a
priſt by heretikes / to be laufully admitted &amp; that this ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſſyon
ought not to be diſamulled or cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged aga<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>in. <pb facs="tcp:4559:31"/>As .S. Hierom
writeth of the church of alex<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dria that at the firſt it was como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly &amp;
gouerned by priſtes &amp; preachers with out any biſſhopes at all.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the mariage of priſtes</head>
               <p>Wher as thei haue forbidde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mariage to priſtes &amp; haue
lade<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the order of priſthode i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitute by god with perpetual chaſtite / 
thei haue done vnlauful<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly &amp; wickedly &amp; like vngodly / tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nical &amp;
da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ble wretches. And bi this act thei haue miniſtred occaſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to all
kyndes of abhominable ſinnes / and moſt filthy &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>numerable luſtes
&amp; vices wherin thei remaine &amp; are drowned as yet. Wherfor li<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ke as
neither we nor thei haue no pour to make a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or a ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of a woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / 
Or vtterly to deſtroy both ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> / eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo haue neitheir we nor
thei no pour to ſeparate the creatures of god one fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a nother or to forbid
the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dwel to gether one with a nother honeſtly &amp; godly in matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny.
And therfor we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in no wiſe neither allowe nor yet abide this co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pelled
ſingle life. but we wil haue mariage to be fte vnto all me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as it is
ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned &amp; i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtitute by god / neither wil we vndoo or hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dre his worck
for .S. Paul ſaith that it is tde de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels doctrine ſo to doo.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the church.</head>
               <p>We wil not gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t the pope with his adhere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes to be the church / 
for thei be not in very dede: &amp; we wil not obey thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs which thei
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d or forbid in the name of the church. for a child of vij. yea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>re 
<pb facs="tcp:4559:32"/> old tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes be to god) doth knowe what the chu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rch is namely that
it is a no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of holy &amp; faithful me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; that is a flock of ſuch
ſhepe as heare the vo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ice of their own paſtor: for thus do our childern
pray / ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g I byleue the holy catholike church &amp;c This holines
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth not in typets / ſhaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> crow<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes / lo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g gownes &amp; ſuch
other foliſſh ceremenys inue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted of their own brayne with out any word of
the holy ſcripture. But it co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiſteth in the word of god &amp; in true
&amp; perfit faith</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>How we are iuſtified &amp; ſaued before god &amp; of good
wockes</head>
               <p>What ſo euer I haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinually taught vntil this day / of
this matter / I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>in no wiſe cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge it / na<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mely that we obteine a newe
&amp; a cleane hart and mynd / thorow faith: &amp; that god wil &amp; doth
accept &amp; cownt us for iuſt &amp; holy for chriſtes ſake our mediator.
And although ſinne is not yet thorowly que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ched / mortifyed &amp; killed in
our fleſſh / yet god wil not impute it to he<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that bileueth ꝑfitely.
&amp; ſu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ch a faith / ſuch a renewyng &amp; remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnes is
neuer without good workes goi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g with him &amp; imꝑfeccyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as yet in
thoſe warkes yet thorow the ſame chriſt &amp; for his ſake it ſhal
not be reputed for ſinne / but the mhole ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both in his ꝑſon &amp;
i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his workes ſhal be called &amp; ſhal be in dede / iuſt &amp; holy o<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly
thorow the grace &amp; mercy i<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> chriſt powre &amp; a<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plifyed p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tuoſly vp on us <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Wherfor We can
not glory nor boſt of the merites of our workes / <pb facs="tcp:4559:32"/>if thei be
co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſidred with the grace &amp; mercy of god: but he that gloryth / let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
glory in the lord / that is to ſay let hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> glory that he hath god merciful
&amp; fauorable vnto hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; ſo is all well. Furthermore we adde this
alſo / that if good workes goo not with faith / it is no true / but a falſe
faith.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of the vowes of monkes frires &amp; ſuch other</head>
               <p>For as moch as the vowes of religios me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do di<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rectly repugne
with the pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipal of our faith they ought to be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; vtterly to take<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
a way. for thei be of the no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber of thoſe thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs wherof chriſt ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth
/ Math 24. ſai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g I am chriſt &amp;c. For he that voweth to lyue after the
religyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>of mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kes &amp; frires he bileueth that he ꝓfeſſeth a more
ꝑfite ſtate of liui<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the como<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſort of chriſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men / &amp;
he go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth about to bryng vnto heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by his workes not only hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelf but other
alſo / &amp; this as moch as to denye chriſt. Thei make this boſt alſo
as Thomas doth that their vowes be be equal vnto baptyme which is a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tumelios
blaſphemy againſt god.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="article">
               <head>Of mans tradicyons</head>
               <p>Whereas the papiſtes affirme that mans tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s be
ꝓfitable vnto remiſſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſinnys or that thei merite &amp;
deſerue euerlaſting ſaluacya<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a wicked &amp; a damnable
blaſphemy. For chriſt ſaith thei honor me in vaine with me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s tradicyons.
Ite<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Paul. Thei refuſe &amp; deuye the truth thorvw the <g ref="char:abpre">p̄</g>ceptes of men. And
more ouer wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as thei ſay that it is deadly ſinne to breake ſuch- 
<pb facs="tcp:4559:33"/>tradicyons / it is a falſe lye. Theſe be the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes &amp;
pri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cipal articles wheri<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I muſt abyde re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine &amp; I wil alſo / by the
grace of god / defend / mai<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teyne &amp; ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euen til my death. And
I ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> not ſee / what I ought to cha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge alter or to yeld in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. If any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
wil yeld &amp; remit any thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let him do it with the perel &amp;
danger of his own co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciens. finally there remaine yet cette<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſceiteful
miſtes of the pope co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerni<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g foliſſh &amp; childiſſh arti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cles as
namely about the halowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of churches &amp; about the baptizing of belllys / of
altars &amp; of al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar ſtonys &amp; of their godfathers &amp; of ſuch as
gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue any momy to ſuch thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs. Which maner of bap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tizi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g ſuch thi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gs is a
very blaſphemy &amp; a deriſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the reuere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of baptyme / 
&amp; therfor it ought not to be ſuffred. Of this nomber alſo are the
articles of the halowi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g of candles palmes / cakes / herbys / otes &amp; ſuch
other. This can not be called nor be in dede any true co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecracyon or
halo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wing but rather a deriſyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>iuring. There are an infinyte
ſort of ſuch other diſteiteful &amp; iug<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gli<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g imaginacyo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s / which we
leaue to their god the pope &amp; to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to honore til their bellys braſt / 
we wil not be voked with ſuch things / but fre in euery condicyon.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>M.D.XLIII.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:4559:33"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
